Register of the Dragiša Nikola Ristić Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Dragiša Nikola Ristić Papers
1941-1980
92077
Ristić, Dragiša Nikola, 1909-
7 manuscript boxes, 1 painting 5.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence and writings, relating primarily to Yugoslav military operations and diplomacy during World War II, and to postwar Yugoslav émigré affairs. Includes postwar correspondence between D. T. Simović and Winston Churchill, and a book-length study by D. N. Ristić relating to Nadezhda Krupskaya and V. I. Lenin.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in increments between 1972 and 2004.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1909 January 9 Born, Veliko Bonjice, Serbia
1928 Graduated, Belgrade Military Academy, rank of second lieutenant, assigned to Yugoslavian air force
1932 Promoted to first lieutenant, Yugoslavian air force
1935 Instructor, non-commissioned officers school
1936 Promoted to second captain, squadron commander
1936-1938, 1940-1941 Aide-de-camp to General Dušan Simović, commander of Yugoslavian air force
1939 Promoted to first captain
1941 January 23 Accompanied General Dušan Simović to a meeting in Belgrade with Colonel William J. Donovan, Franklin D. Roosevelt's representative in Europe
1941 March 23 Yugoslav Prime Minister Cvetković signed the Tripartite Pact with Nazi Germany
1941 March 27 Took part in the coup led by General Dušan Simović to overthrow the government of Prince Paul and Cvetković. The 17-year-old Peter II was appointed king, and Simović became the new prime minister
1941 April 6 Germans bombarded Belgrade, began invasion of Yugoslavia
1941 April 14 Received assignment to escort King Peter II out of Yugoslavia to safety, and flew him to Athens. Two days later, Simović, Ristić, and the King flew to Alexandria
1941 April-June In Jerusalem, where Yugoslavian government-in-exile was based until it moved to London
1942 March Transferred to the Yugoslav military mission in Canada and the United States, and was based variously at Ottawa, Washington, Nashville, and Windsor, Ontario. While in Windsor, enrolled at Wayne State University in Detroit
1943-1945 Transferred to Yugoslavian forces based in Cairo, and while there, enrolled in the American University
1945 May 26 Honorable discharge from the Yugoslavian armed forces, rank of major
1946-1948 Returned to the United States, employed by U.S. Steel Products Company, Los Angeles, and enrolled at University of California, Los Angeles
1950 Graduated, bachelor's degree in political science, University of California, Los Angeles
1951 Employed as instructor of Serbo-Croatian language at the U.S. Army Language School, Presidio of Monterey, California
1953 Graduated, master's degree in political science, University of California, Los Angeles
1955 Studied at the Faculté de Droit, University of Paris, while researching book on the Yugoslavian revolution of 1941
1966 Published Yugoslavia's Revolution of 1941 (Pennsylvania State University Press)
1972-1973 Studied in doctoral program for political science, Western Colorado University
2004 Died, Monterey, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Dragiša N. Ristić, acquired in increments between 1972 and 2004, document his military career in the Yugoslavian air force, with a special emphasis on his role as a protégé of General Dušan Simović. Simović was one of the leaders of the coup of March 27, 1941, which overthrew the pro-German government in Belgrade. Ristić was an aide-de-camp to General Simović, and as such, was both a participant in and eyewitness to the events surrounding the coup.
In the years following the war, Ristić sought to document the events of this period, with an eye to defending the reputation of his mentor. Having spent the war years in London, Simović returned to Yugoslavia in 1945, and lived in Belgrade until his death in 1962. During the 1950s, Simović maintained a steady correspondence with Ristić, who by then had settled in Monterey, California, and designated him to write his biography. To facilitate this, Simović transferred his wartime diary and manuscript memoir to Ristić, both of which can be found in a separate collection under Simović's name at the Hoover Institution Archives. During that period, Ristić began corresponding with and interviewing many of the surviving key figures from the Yugoslavian government before the coup, including Vladko Maćek, Slobodan Jovanović, Prince Paul, and others.
The Biographical File contains various personal documents, but also includes fairly extensive wartime diaries of Ristić from his period in North America and Egypt. These diaries were written initially in Serbian, but Ristić switched to using English in 1942, when he began studying English at Wayne State University in Detroit. Fragments of a never-completed memoir can also be found in this series.
The Correspondence contains the bulk of the surviving research material for his book on the 1941 coup. It consists of correspondence and interviews primarily from the 1950s, including his extensive correspondence with Simović. The Writings contains various fragmentary works and essays, but also a lengthy unpublished history of the Russian Revolution, a topic that greatly interested Ristić over the years. Also included in this series are theses from his academic career at the University of California, Los Angeles and Western Colorado University, works that also are connected to the history of the 1941 coup. The Subject File and Printed Material contain additional material that he used in his research. The collection also contains an oil Painting depicting General Dušan Simović, by Yugoslavian artist Veljko Stanojevic, which Ristić displayed in his home in Monterey.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series, Biographical File, Correspondence and Interview Notes, Writings, Subject File, Printed Material, and Painting.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.; Yugoslavs--United States.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924.; Krupskaya, Nadezhda Konstantinovna, 1869-1939.; Simović, Dušan T., 1882-1962.; Churchill, Winston, Sir, 1874-1965.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1941-1965, undated
  Diaries in Serbian and English, 1942-1945; draft fragments of a projected memoir, and various personal documents from his military, civilian, and academic careers, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Academic records, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address book, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Application for fellowship, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards and memberships, 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Diary
    - 1942 May 12 - July 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1942 July 3 - October 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1942 October 12 - 1943 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1943 February 19 - September 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1943 September 22 - 1944 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1944 June 2 - December 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - English lesson book, 1944-1945. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes diary entries, draft letters, and memoir fragments, graded by instructor
  - Memoir drafts
    - "From Autobiography: A Record of (Foreign) Language Experiences,", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "A Supplementary: The Author's Recollections,", undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "My Memoria,", undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Untitled draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Untitled fragments, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Military documents, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Passports and visas, 1941-1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Personnel records, 1945-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of family, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence and Interview Notes, 1927-1996; (bulk 1951-1961).
  Correspondence and summaries of interviews with exiled Yugoslavian political leaders and others, primarily related to research for his book on the 1941 coup, Yugoslavia's Revolution of 1941, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Also contains a few files of family and personal correspondence from the 1970s through the 1990s.
  - Unidentified, 1942-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Churchill, Winston, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cvetković, Dragiša, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dinić, Miloj, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Djurović, Tosa, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Dragosavlević, S., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dzaković, M., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Gavrilović, Milan, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Graham, Malbone, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jevtić, Bogoljub, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Jovanović, Slobodan
    - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Interview notes, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Krek, Miho, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Maćek, Vladko
    - Correspondence, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Interview notes, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Maksimović, Boža, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Miletić, B. S., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Milovonović, Milena, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Mogilevsky, Ivan, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Nikitović, Dr., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pantelić, Vojislav, Maj., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Papić, Stevan, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Paul, Prince of Yugoslavia, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Pavelić, Ante Smith, 1956-1967 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Pavlović, Paja, Gen., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Peter II, King of Yugoslavia, 1943-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Petrović, Branislav, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Purić, G., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Radusinović, Mihailo, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rakoćević, Milo, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ristić, Katarina, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ristić, Leposava (mother), 1927 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Savić, Dragutin, 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Simović, Dušan, 1951-1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stanojević, Veljko, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sterdjević, G., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subotić, I., 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sumenković, Ilija
    - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Interview notes, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Veselinović, Božidar and Srbaslava (brother-in-law and sister)
    - 1981-1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1990-1996 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Visacki, Ljubos, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Vukćević, Petar, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Vuković, Ivona, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Yugoslavian air force, Cairo, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Živanović, Zagorka (sister), 1966-1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Writings, 1942-1973, undated.
  Various essays and book drafts on topics related to modern Yugoslavian history (primarily interwar years and events leading up to the coup of March 27, 1941), and the Russian Revolution, arranged alphabetically by title
  - Miscellaneous fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Notes for a history of the Yugoslavian revolution, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Conclusion to book on Russian Revolution, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Typescript
  - Marxism, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Preface to book about Yugoslavia, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Work on Yugoslavian foreign relations, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Account of the Belgrade Revolution,", undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "The Adriatic Question,", undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Djeneral Dušan Simović i Njegov Istoriski Cin,", 1942 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Epilogue: Pen, Pencil, and Sweat,", undated. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Autobiographical work intended as epilogue to planned book
  - "The February Revolution, the Tsar and the Formation of the Provisional Government," doctoral project, Western Colorado University, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Foreign Relations of Yugoslavia, 1914-1934," master's thesis, University of California, Los Angeles, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Imperial Russia and Serbia,", undated. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Draft. In Serbian
  - "A Lecture Syllabus for Yugoslavia's Revolution of 1941, EDCS-700 Independent Study Curriculum," Western Colorado University, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Nadezhda Krupskaya and Lenin,", undated
    - Pages 1-163 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Pages 165-329 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Pages 330-500 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Pages 501-726 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Pages 727-938 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Pages 939-1061, plus Chapter XXIV (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Pages 1062-1271 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Pages 1272-1464 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Additional notes and fragments of draft (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Oktobarska Revolucija,", 1962-1964. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Manuscript drafts
  - "Opening Stage of the Triune State,", undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Poseta Pukovnika Williama Donovana,", undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Russia's Great Revolution,", undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Trieste in International Politics,", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Turkey: The Period of Mustapha Kemal Pasha,", undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Subject File, 1941-1956, undated.
  Notes and other material, primarily related to Yugoslavian leadership in exile during World War II, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Coup of March 27, 1941, 1941-1956 and undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Grol, Milan, 1945 and undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Knežević, Živan, 1944-1955 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Nedić, Milan, 1941 and undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Simović, Miloš, 1941-1942 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Unattributed report from Yugoslav mission in Washington, to Slobodan Jovanović, London, Sep-42 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Printed Material, 1942-1957, undated.
  Arranged alphabetically by title
  - Prince Paul of Yugoslavia (printed in Great Britain, unattributed), circa 1942. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Includes tipped-in letter to Ristić from Dušan Simović, 1957
  - Samoubistvo Jugoslavije, by Danilo Gregorić. Belgrade: Izdavaćko i Prometno A.D. Jugoistok, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Copy owned and annotated by Du*san Simović
  - Yugoslavia at War (Yugoslav Documents, No. 2, Collection of official statements). London: Yugoslav Information Department, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Painting, undated. (Art racks Art racks)
  Portrait in oil of General Dušan Simović, by Veljko Stanojevic, undated